Finding Aid for Hermann and Hilde Pinkus Papers, 1930-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hermann and Hilde Pinkus Papers 1930-1982
Pinkus, Hermann.
1 oversize folder
(in 5 boxes)
4 linear feet
2012011 Aa 2
Hermann Pinkus and Hilde Hensel Pinkus were German immigrants who worked as dermatologists and allergists in the greater Detroit area. The collection includes records from the Detroit Dermatological Society and material related to the Pinkus’s participation in professional societies and their research interests, including thorium X and amino acids.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Walter Pinkus (donor no. 8001 ) in May 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research except for client related files in boxes 4 and 5, which are closed until 2036 to 2046 depending on the date of the individual volume.
Hermann Pinkus and Hilde Hensel Pinkus were German immigrants who worked as dermatologists and allergists in the greater Detroit area.
Hermann Pinkus was born in Berlin on November 18, 1905. He received a doctorate from the University of Berlin in 1930, and a Master of Science degree in experimental surgery from the University of Michigan in 1935. Hilde Hensel followed Pinkus to American in 1935 and they were married shortly thereafter. Hilde also completed a Master of Science degree. at the University of Michigan. Following their graduation, both Hilde and Hermann completed their residencies at Wayne County Hospital. Both later joined the staff at Monroe Hospital.
While at Monroe Hospital, Hermann Pinkus opened a dermatopathological specimen analysis service. He left his practice in 1950 to pursue cancer research at the Michigan Cancer Institute and took up a teaching post at Wayne County College (later Wayne State University). Pinkus also held a Visiting Professorship at Glasgow University Scotland. Both Hilde and Herman Pinkus were active in professional organizations, regularly attending conference and publishing on their research interests.
Herman Pinkus passed away in 1985, and Hilde Pinkus passed away in 1995.
The Hilde and Hermann Pinkus Papers (4 linear feet) are arranged in the following series: Professional Societies and Activities (1.25 linear feet); Topical Files (.75 linear feet); Miscellaneous (.25 linear feet); and Experimental Files (1.75 linear feet). This collection is particularly strong in its documentation of research practices and the treatment of various dermatological issues during the first half the 20th century.
Subjects:
Pinkus, Hilde Hensel.; Pinkus, Hermann.; Air--Pollution--Michigan.; Dermatologists--Michigan.; Pathology.; Skin--Diseases--Treatment.; Detroit Dermatological Society.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Professional Societies and Activities
  The Professional Societies and Activities (1.25 linear feet) series documents Hilde and Hermann Pinkus's involvement with various professional societies and their attendance at conferences. This series also includes records of the Detroit Dermatological Society.
  - Conferences
    - American Dermatologic Society for Allergy and Immunology Annual Meeting 1979 (Box 1)
    - Atlanta Dermatological Association Quarterly Meeting 1979 (Box 1)
    - International Congress of Dermatology XII 1962 (Box 1)
    - International Congress of Dermatology XIII 1967 (Box 1)
    - International Congress of Pediatric Dermatology 1976 (Box 1)
    - International Society of Tropical Dermatology -- Fourth World Congress (Box 1)
    - Michigan State Medical Society Meeting 1976 (Box 1)
  - Societies
    - American College of Allergists 1978 (Box 1)
    - American Medical Women's Association 1939-1949 (Box 1)
    - Association of Allergists for Mycological Investigations
      - Correspondence 1956-1976, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - General 1979 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Dermatological Society
      - Chronological Files
        - 1934-1935 (Box 1)
        - 1935-1937 (Box 1)
        - 1937-1938 (Box 1)
      - Minutes
        - October 15, 1935 (Box 1)
        - December 17, 1935 (Box 1)
        - January 21, 1936 (Box 1)
        - February 18, 1936 (Box 1)
        - March 17, 1936 (Box 1)
        - April 22, 1936 (Box 1)
        - September 24, 1936 (Box 1)
        - October 27, 1936 (Box 1)
        - November 17, 1936 (Box 1)
        - January 19, 1937 (Box 1)
        - February, 1937 (Box 1)
        - March 16, 1937 (Box 1)
        - April 28, 1937 (Box 1)
        - October 19, 1937 (Box 1)
        - January, 1938 (Box 1)
        - February 15, 1938 (Box 1)
        - March, 1938 (Box 2)
        - April 20, 1938 (Box 2)
        - September 21, 1938 (Box 2)
        - October 26, 1943 (Box 2)
        - January 19, 1944 (Box 2)
        - March 21, 1944 (Box 2)
      - Society Transactions 1934-1935 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Allergy Society
      - Air Pollution Committee 1966 (Box 2)
      - General 1976 (Box 2)
    - Monroe County Medical Society 1957-1959 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files (.75 linear feet) include publications prepared by Hilde and Hermann Pinkus and material related to their research interests, including files on Thorium X, amino acids, mold, and air pollution. These files include correspondence, publications, and research notes.
  - Airborne mold spores
    - Correspondence 1969-1974, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Fusarium vasinfectum paper and tables 1973 (Box 2)
  - Compliment fixation 1937-1939 (Box 2)
  - Dundee Air Pollution 1970-1977 (Box 2)
  - Molds Association 1961-1970 (Box 2)
  - Nitrogen Equilibrium in Amino Acids
    - Complications (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1941-1942 (Box 2)
    - Disposition of Amino Acid Nitrogen tables (Box 2)
    - "Maintenance of Nitrogen Equilibrium by Intravenous Administration of Amino Acids," 1942 (Box 2)
    - "Maintenance of Nitrogen Equilibrium of Amino Acids Administered Parentally," 1940 (Box 2)
    - Nitrogen Balance Studies (Box 2)
    - Notes (Box 2)
  - Occupational Skin Disease 1962 (Box 2)
  - Oral Pollen (Box 2)
  - Organoid Tumors 1962 (Box 2)
  - Thorium X
    - Case notes 1939 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1939-1941, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Glass slides (Box 2)
  - Tobacco 1962-1968 (Box 2)
  - Uticaria 1958-1960 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous (.25 linear feet) series is primarily composed of biographical material, press clippings, and individual research publications.
  - 65th Birthday Celebration
    - Audio material (Box 2)
    - Biographical material 1970 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1970 (Box 2)
    - Photo of HP with Mrs. Isidor Ebstein, M.D. on occasion of his 655th birthday (Folder 1)
  - Clippings (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1972-1982 (Box 3)
  - Dissertation 1930, in German (Box 3)
  - Eloise Hospital (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
    - Portraits (Box 3)
    - Awards (Box 3)
    - Early and miscellaneous (Box 3)
      include copyprint of family scene, 1919
    - Dermatology informational exhibits, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - HP with Wayne State University Dept. of Dermatology staff members and residents (Box 3)
  - Pinkus lecture 1980 (Box 3)
  - Travel (Box 3)
  - Veterans Administration Distinguished Physician Award Nomination 1978 (Box 3)
- Experimental Records
  Some of the slide notebooks and clinical photographs contain patient information. This indicated material is closed to researchers until the year 2046.
  The Experimental Files (1.75 linear feet) includes observational records kept by Hermann Pinkus, slide notebooks with morphological drawings and observational notations, and clinical photographs documenting various cases treated by Pinkus.
  - Records of Experiments, 1 volume (Box 3)
  - Records of Tissue Cultures, 1 volume (Box 3)
  - Lab books of Hilde Pinkus relating to experiments on rats 1935-1936, 3 volumes (Box 3)
  - Slide Notebooks, 7 volumes (Box 4)
    Closed to research until 2046 ]
  - Slide Notebooks (cont.), 7 volumes (Box 5)
  - Clinical Photographs 1936-1939 (Box 5)
    Closed to research until 2039 ]